pain, joint stiffness, reduce range of
motion. Is it me getting out of a chair
or is it osteoarthritis? We'll discuss
the first one another time. This time,
let's get into a fascinating new
discovery related to how your cells are
poisoning the tissue around your joints,
causing the joint instability that
people experience with age, but
especially with arthritis. More
specifically, researchers seem to think
that our cells are using iron to poison
the muscle around our joints. Why do
they think that? And if it's true, is
there anything that we might be able to
do to stop it? Arthritis tends to strike
in specific joints. So, the researchers
of this massive study measured the
muscle size around the arthritis
affected joint and the muscle size
around the unaffected joint of people
with arthritis. In addition, they
measured the muscle strength. So we can
see both here. The orange dots are the
arthritis affected joint and the blue
the left side are the healthy unaffected
joints. In both measures, muscle size or
muscle strength, the arthritis affected
joint did worse. That probably isn't a
huge surprise. So why is that? Well,
there's no denying that it could be to
any number of reasons. If a person
experiences more pain, they're less
likely to favor that joint, which would
lead to some mild disuse, reductions in
muscle size and strength. I think that
is a safe assumption. However, that's
not the only explanation. For one,
there's an increase in inflammation,
total body. But they also noticed
something peculiar related to the immune
system. For one, while our immune system
is made up of many cells, dendritic
cells, T- cells, B cells, and many
others, the only ones that were abundant
in the afflicted joint were the common
immune cell called a macrofase. The
reason that's peculiar is that it
indicates potential specificity, as in
these particular cells are there for a
reason that is unique to them without
recruiting other immune cells. So to
summarize simply, the muscle around the
arthritic joint is smaller and weaker
and there's a peculiar accumulation of a
specific type of immune cell in that
region. So what are these macrofase
cells doing there? What does it have to
do with the poisoning? And will this be
turning into a Shakespearean play? Well,
the cells are actually deranged. They're
crazy, I tell you. But seriously, these
immune cells are suffering from more
gene damage and they're more scesscent.
That means that the cells have more
damage to the genetic material or the
genetic information found within them.
And they've turned into zombie cells
where they shut themselves down. So
these zombie macrofase cells are
suffering from multiple problems causing
them to be dysfunctional inside the
muscle around the joint. Doesn't sound
good. But how is that affecting the
joint itself, the muscle? Well, the
researchers took samples of muscle from
people with arthritis and discovered
that their affected joint, the muscle
around it, has an unusually high
concentration of iron in it. seen here.
The orange is the arthritis condition.
The blue is the nonarththritis
condition. And the amount of iron is
greater in the arthritis condition. The
reason we're talking about iron here is
because iron in its unbound form is
highly reactive as in it interacts with
the structure of the cell and does
tremendous damage to it. Now, all that
damage to the cell leads to a process
called ferroptosis, which is an iron
overload in the cell causing the cell to
self-destruct. So the researchers
hypothesize that the scesscent
macrofasages, this is a graphic from the
paper by the way, take up red blood
cells containing bound iron in the form
of hemoglobin. They liberate the iron
from hemoglobin now making it highly
reactive free iron and then kick that
iron back out of the scesscent macrofase
which then unfortunately gets taken up
by the muscle cells inducing
ferroptosis. muscle cell death from iron
overload. Honestly, I'm only showing you
the main highlights of the study, and
there's a ton more that the researchers
get into, like the removal of
scinesscent cells, the impact of
reducing a particular protein called BCL
XL has, and even encouraging the
production of a supplementable molecule
has on protecting the muscle around the
joint. I do cover all that in the
extended version of this video that
you're watching along with the full
article that accompanies it. If you're
interested including all these perks,
join the Physionic Insiders. It's where
the serious science takes place. Well,
not too serious. We still allow the
occasional mirth. You can join the uh
Physionic Insiders using the link in the
description if you're interested. Okay,
we now know the detrimental effects
these scesscent macroofasages have on
our muscle, killing it, stressing it
through poisoning via free iron and so
on. What can we do? Actually, a number
of things. some more general and some
more specific. As limiting as
osteoarthritis and arthritis as a whole
can be, whatever exercise is manageable,
that should be priority number one for
an obvious reason and a nonobvious
reason. All exercise will help maintain
muscle mass and structural integrity
around the affected joint. Zero doubt
about that. However, exercise is also
known to reduce scinesscent markers
known as SASPs throughout the body and
inflammation as a whole. So, if
possible, strongly encouraged to
exercise a few times per week. Second,
there are anti-inflammatory diets out
there. The Mediterranean diet is one
example, a ketogenic as another. Both
have good evidence reducing symptoms of
arthritis. Third, a bit more specific,
is to keep an eye on a blood metric
called HBA1C, which is a measure of
longerterm blood sugar levels. There is
some evidence of a relationship with
higher HBA1C and osteoarthritis
progression, likely because HBA1C is a
decent though not perfect proxy of AES,
a molecule known to exacerbate
scinesscent cells like what we've been
discussing. So maintaining a lower HBA1C
by the two points mentioned prior could
help reduce inflammatory and
proineesscent state of the macrofasages.
I'd like to see direct evidence, but it
certainly wouldn't harm. Finally, the
researchers mentioned CoQ10 as a
potential for benefit as well. They
indicate across a number of experiments
that CoQ10 reverses many of these
negative effects. I go into a lot more
detail on how CoQ10 is implicated. It's
a fascinating mechanism for the insiders
if you're interested. But the bottom
line is that I couldn't find any studies
in humans looking at osteoarthritis, but
there are some in rheumatoid arthritis.
So confirmed to a degree. I'll mention
another supplement in a bit too. So all
this put together, what's the short of
it? The study indicates that
osteoarthritis is linked to reduced
muscle size and strength around the
affected joint. This happens at least in
part due to the accumulation of
scinsesscent zombie immune cells that
slowly poison the muscle cells by
overloading them with free iron which is
highly damaging and causes stress and
death to the muscle cells. The mechanism
is still hypothetical although some
evidence exists even if it's incomplete.
We can reduce the negative consequences
of these scesscent immune cells and
preserve muscle by a exercising as
possible, b eating an anti-inflammatory
diet, c keeping hbaw1c levels within
normal range, and d possibly through
CoQ10 supplementation, though that needs
further evidence. However, one
supplement that I like that I find
extremely beneficial for several
arthritis conditions is curcumin, the
one that I go in depth right here. I
hope this fascinated you as much as it
did me. Thanks for tuning in.